<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The teachers of the vvorld unvailed. VVherein the ground of their ministry is manifested, both in doctrine and practice, to be out of the light which cometh from Christ, in the witchcraft deceiving the people. Where as in a glasse they are seene to be such that the prophets woo was against, and which Christ gave warning of, and the apostles saw in their dayes enter the world, and are now in this day manifest to the children of light, / and declared against by G.F. that all people may from them turne. With a briefe declaration of the seed of evill doers, which from time to time have withstood the truth of God in all ages. As also certaine queries given forth touching Q. Maries law made for defence of the priests and Jesuits, by which the priests and false teachers of this nation now guard themselves, and persecute the children of light even to death by long and tedious imprisonments in holes and dungeons.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84815</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872231</idno>
  <idno type="VID">168387</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240948078</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1924A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E881_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29430</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872231</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99872231e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84815)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E881[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The teachers of the vvorld unvailed. VVherein the ground of their ministry is manifested, both in doctrine and practice, to be out of the light which cometh from Christ, in the witchcraft deceiving the people. Where as in a glasse they are seene to be such that the prophets woo was against, and which Christ gave warning of, and the apostles saw in their dayes enter the world, and are now in this day manifest to the children of light, / and declared against by G.F. that all people may from them turne. With a briefe declaration of the seed of evill doers, which from time to time have withstood the truth of God in all ages. As also certaine queries given forth touching Q. Maries law made for defence of the priests and Jesuits, by which the priests and false teachers of this nation now guard themselves, and persecute the children of light even to death by long and tedious imprisonments in holes and dungeons.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons at the signe of the Bull and Mouth neere Aldersgate.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G.F. = George Fox.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8 June.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Freedom of religion --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168387:1"/>
            <p>THE TEACHERS OF THE WORLD UNVAILED.</p>
            <p>Wherein the ground of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry is manifested, both in doctrine and practice, to be out of the light which cometh from <hi>Christ, in the Witchcraft deceiving the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where as in a Glasse they are seene to be such that the Prophets woo was against, and which Christ gave warning of, and the Apostles saw in their dayes enter the world, and are now in this day manifest to the Children of light, and declared against by <hi>G. F.</hi> that all people may <hi>from them turne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a briefe Declaration of the seed of Evill doers, which from time to time have withstood the truth of God in all ages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As also</hi> Certaine <hi>Queries</hi> given forth touching Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Law made for defence of the Priests and Jesuits, by which the Priests and false Teachers of this Nation now guard themselves, and persecute the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light even to death by long and tedious Imprisonments in holes and dungeons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the Signe of the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> neere <hi>Aldersgate.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168387:2"/>
            <p>YOu that doe reade this may see the Ministry of the world which is now standing to be that which the Apostles saw creepe in before their decease, which they that were in the life bid turne away from, which in all ages was with it jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and where the Spirit of the Lord was raised up in the hearts, it brought them to stand a witnesse against it in all ages past, such as have gott the forme of the words but are strangers from the Spirit that gave it forth; but now that which the Apostle saw then creep in who was in the life, now is seene with the light and judged, and such are the false Prophets that receive not the light &amp; believe not in it, and such are the deceivers that receive not the light and believe not in it, and such are the Antichrists that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not the light and believe not in it, which then came into the world, which now are in the world, and against the light stand which enlighteneth every man that cometh into the world, and such are the false Christs that believe not in the light, that should come if it were possible to deceive the very Elect, that cryes lo here and lo there, which the true Christ that enlighteneth every one that cometh into the world, saith, <hi>goe not forth,</hi> and his true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster saith, <hi>Christ is in you, except you be Reprobates.</hi> Now he that is the Reprobate hates the light, though it shew him his evill deeds, and them to it he will not bring, because the light will condemne him, therefore it is his Condemnation, so he receiveth not Christ, he is in the state of <hi>Esau,</hi> hated of God, growes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, which is a place for <hi>Dragons,</hi> and finds no place for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. But God the life is raising up in his people which the Scripture was given forth from, with which they see and know it, with the same light that the Apostles were in that saw it creepe in, which light judgeth and condemneth it, which answers the light in every man.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168387:2"/>
            <head>The <hi>Teachers</hi> of the World unvailed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He day hath made manifest to the Children of light, and to the Children of light the day hath manifested error, the false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the Antichrists, and the false teachers that be in the world out of the light which cometh from Christ who is not of the world, not owning the light nor suffering others them that be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their teaching to owne the light, but tells them it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> naturall; so such as had the Scriptures, <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets words, which stood praying in the Synagogues, which have the cheifest seats in the Assembly, which were called of men <hi>Master,</hi> these were them to whom Christ would send wise men and Scribes, and they should scourge them in their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and persecute them from Citty to Citty. Now we doe see with the light that the Ministry standing in this age is in the steppes of them that Christ speaks off, though they have gotten the Apostles words, &amp; Christs words to talke off, yet they are found in the steppes of the Pharisees and cheife Priests in their way and steppes, persecuting, causing to be put out of the Synagogues, persecuting from Citty to Citty, by such as are called of men <hi>Master,</hi> have the cheifest place in the Assembly, stand praying in the Synagogues, which Christ cryed woe against. So we seeing them here out of the life of the Prophets who saw Christ and <hi>Moses,</hi> and out of the life of Christ, and out of the life of the Apostles, in the stepps of them that they witnessed against, though they call theselves Ministers of Christ, yet they are them that are climbed up another way, who are not in the Prophets way, nor in Christs way; So they that are climbed up another way are the thieves, <hi>another way,</hi> marke, that is out of Christ the way, the light. Now with Christs words this Ministry standing is measured and their wayes, and so to be out of Christ the way; Such the Children of light that be in the light see to be thieves and robbers, and so come to steale and destroy.</p>
            <p>First out of the Prophets way, they are such that have not heard the voice of God immediately from heaven, as the Prophets did, as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed, so such the Lord never sent, but are in the divination of their owne hearts, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. And such as the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> cryed against, <hi>that beare rule by their meanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>which held up the horrible filthy thing committed in the Land, and people loved to have it so;</hi> for which said God, <hi>shall not I visit for these things;</hi> and saith the Prophet, <hi>Come to the good old way,</hi> who saw them here out of the good old way? and here we see the Ministers of the world out of the good old way in the way that the Prophets witnessed against.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:168387:3"/>
            <p>Againe,
<note place="margin">Isa 56.</note> they are such that are out of the Prophets way, such as seek for the gaine from their Quarter, who are greedy dumb doggs, which thinke they have never enough; the Prophet there doth not give them the name of men, but calls them doggs, greedy dumb doggs, every one looking for his owne way, and for his gaine from his Quarter, which we see in this age with the light therefore to be cryed against. And the Prophet questioned the people and asked them <hi>why they spent their money for that which was not bread, and their labour for that which satisfied not? And bid them come freely without money and without price every one that did thirst, that their soules might live; and I will make an everlasting Covenant with you, even the sure mercies of David.</hi> Now reade this and understand whose soules live not, who are not yet come to the everlasting Covenant? who are yet spending your money for that which is not bread, and are not satisfied, and such are cryed against now in this age by the Children of light, who witnesse Christ and the Prophets.</p>
            <p>Againe,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 34.</note> you may see they are out of the Prophets way, who cryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst such that sought for the fleece, and made a prey upon them in the cloudy darke day, and so they doe now, but saith the Lord, <hi>I will seek my sheepe where they have been scattered this cloudy dark day, and gather them, from their mouthes, they shall not be a prey to them any longer, and I will feed them upon the top of the mountaines, for in the cloudy dark day my sheepe wandred from mountaine to hill, and were made a prey upon;</hi> but saith the Lord, <hi>I will seek them out and gather and feed them upon the top of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and there shall be one fold and one Shepheard;</hi> and this hath the Lord done: and those that seeke for the fleece and the wooll are denyed and cryed against, which makes a prey upon the people.</p>
            <p>Againe,
<note place="margin">Mic. 3.</note> they be out of the Prophets way, who witnessed against such Priests as divine for money, and taught for money, and yet leaned upon the Lord, and say, <hi>Is not the Lord among us?</hi> and they did preach peace to the people, but if they did not put into their mouthes they prepared warre against them, and these that did divine for money, and taught for money, and prophesie for money, that prepared warre against the people if they did not put into their mouthes; Such builded up <hi>Sion</hi> with blood and <hi>Jerusalem</hi> with iniquitie, and for the cause of such builders <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was brought to be in heapes, and <hi>Sion</hi> to be ploughed up like a field, and their highest place like a forrest, as hath been fullfilled in this our age which are standing in the selfe same stepps out of the Prophets. And the saying of <hi>Jeremy</hi> comes to be fulfilled here, <hi>Shall not my soule be avenged on such a Nation as this?</hi> Here the Lord will scatter them that are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by such as the Light makes it manifest, and such cheife Priests and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168387:3"/>Pharisees as were called of men Master, stood praying in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, had the chiefest place in the Assembly, gett a gathered people, and Elders, and Members, and Doctors, but these were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Christ the life, and these were not gathered by him, such as were called of men Master, stood praying in the Synagogues, had the chiefest place in the Assembly then and now, but were and are out of his way, and over such he wept, and said, <hi>I would have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered thee as a henne gathereth her Chic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ens under her wings, and you would not.</hi> Now here you may all see those that be in their stepps be not gathered with Christ, but are out of his way. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heed all you Powers of the earth what you hold up, for such as are not gathered with him, he will scatter and lay wast, and be out of his life, though they be Elders Members, gathered peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, chiefe Priests, Doctors, and the worlds great disputers, such will with the life and power of the Lord Jesus Christ be scattered, brought to shame and confusion and condemnation, with the light which cometh from him who is not of the world, though they have all the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>The Teachers of the world are such that deny the light which every man is inlightened withall and saith, that every man is not enlightened that cometh into the world with the light, so heere they deny that which was given to man to believe, and they that deny the light, deny him from whence it comes and the Father; And they that deny the light which lighteth every one that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world, deny the salvation, for none see the salvation but with the light which comes from Christ the Saviour, who gives every one a light to see their sinnes, who saves them from their sinnes; so they that deny the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, are they that shutt up the kingdome of heaven against men, and goe not in themselves, nor suffer others, for none come to the kingdome but such as owne the light which comes from Christ the second <hi>Adam,</hi> for as all men not owning this light are yet dead in <hi>Adam,</hi> and so in darknesse driven from God who is light, but every man being enlightened with a light that comes from Christ the second <hi>Adam,</hi> that he might believe, <hi>he that doth believe shall not abide in darknesse, but shall have the light of life, he that doth not believe abideth in darknesse and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; so they entered not into rest because of unbeliefe;</hi> for none en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the rest, but who believe the light to come to Christ, the rest, the peace, him by whom the world was made before it was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168387:4"/>made, who is not of the world, these see all the troubles where they are in the world, that is the deceiver which is out of the light and abides not in the truth, so doe not owne the light, nor will suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer none of you to owne, there is the Prince of the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse which goes under the Chaine into the pit, and so they that doe not believe that Christ hath enlightened every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world, they cannot preach the truth the word of life, nor the hope of glory, nor the way to the Father: For as all dyed in <hi>Adam</hi> as drove from God, Christ the second <hi>Adam</hi> the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, the truth, the way to the Father, the God of all truth, so none comes to see the way to the Father, but such as come to see the light which comes from the second <hi>Adam;</hi> but they that deny the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, are yet dead in their sinnes, and the uncircumcision of the flesh, see not themselves but are in darknesse, and may talke of all the words declared from the Spirit of truth, and Christ the way, but they themselves out of it, these are the Deceivers who mind earthly things, who serve not our Lord Jesus Christ, but their owne bellies, who through good words &amp; faire speeches deceive the hearts of the simple, the hearts of the simple are deceived by them that be out of the light for that is the Deceiver, as I said before, who is out of the light, out of the truth, and did not abide in it, now he rules which is out of the truth in all the Children of disobedience that be disobedient to the light which comes from Christ the truth, which the Children of the light walke in, and there is the murderer, and they are brought to doe his lusts, though they may talke of the good words, and so there the Devill may bring Scripture for his owne ends, for where the truth is obeyed he is cast out, and there hath no rule, nor can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not worke, but he workes in the Children of disobedience, and comes with a pretence of godlinesse, which out of truth, and so getts into the Children of Disobedience, but the Children of light discerne him, and know that the wrath of God comes upon the Children of disobedience, where he that is out of the truth, enters and works, there he lifts up in the pride and the presumption where the light is disobeyed and hated, which should have kept it out and judged it, for the children of disobedience being disobedient to that which the Children of light walke in, that which is out of the truth comes in, so they come to be servants to him who is out of the truth, which reignes and rules in the Children of Disobedience,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168387:4"/>which is judged and seene with the Children that are in the light, for being disobedient darknes rules and the understanding is dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, their foolish hearts are darkened, and minds alienated, and come to be estranged from the Covenant of light, and life of God, but the Covenant of God and his life being received, all that is judged with the life of God which abode not in the truth, which gets into the Children of disobedience and condemned out.</p>
            <p>The Ministers of the world say, Revelations are past and ceased, and immediate inspiration, Christ saith,
<note place="margin">Math. 11.</note>
               <hi>No man knowes the Sunne but the Father, neither knowes any man the Father but the Sonne, and he to whom the Sonne will reveale him;</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you which call your selves Ministers and deny Revelation, you deny the Father, and you that deny the Father deny the Sonne also, so are them that be in the transgression, to which you are not to be said God-speed, neither to be received into the houses, least they be pertakers of your evill deeds; for that which is in the transgression is in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, <hi>For no man knowes the Sonne but the Father, neither knoweth any man the Father save the Sonne, and he to whomsoever the Son will reveale him.</hi> Now here the Sonne to whom all things are delivered of his Father, must reveale the Father before the Father be known, so you that deny Revelation have denyed your knowing of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; For the Pharisees which you be in the stepps off, they heard the Sonnes words outwardly, and the Prophets words, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles words, but they know not the Father, neither the Sonne, but to whom the Sonne doth reveale the Father, they know who receive him both the Father and the Sonne. So you may see here that many had the Scripture but knew not neither Father nor Sonne, neither doe they now untill the Sonne hath revealed him, he that hath the Sonne hath the Father also, and how can you know the Sonne or revelation, who owneth not the light which the Sonne enlighteneth every man that commeth into the world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and so you deny revelations, and you that deny the one deny the other, and keepe people from waiting upon the Sonne, keepe people from the light who reveales the Father, you which neither have the Father nor the Sonne, who be out of the truth of him that abode not in it; So you are the Antichrists that should come, that are against Christ, and that is the Antichrist which is out of truth, which should come into the world.</p>
            <p>Againe, you that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the world which deny perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you are no Ministers of Christ
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168387:5"/>that he hath sent forth, for them which he sent forth to whom he gave gifts, their Ministry was <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, the edifying of the body, till they all come into the unity of the Faith, to the measure of the stature of the fulnesse of Christ.</hi> Now here you have cleared your selves out of the way which the Ministers of Christ were in who deny perfection, you have denyed your selves to be in that Ministry which the Apostles were in for the edifying of the Saints, and for the perfecting of them. So you are seene with all the Children of light and denyed, which are contrary to truth, and conformable to the world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You are no Ministers of that offering which hath <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected for ever them that are sanctified;</hi> And often saith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle; <hi>Finally Brethren, be perfect, be of one mind, stand perfect and compleate in all the will of God, that I may present every man perfect in Christ Jesus,</hi> saith the Apostle, <hi>who was sent to turne them from darknesse to light. And after you have suffered a while, settle you, strengthen you, stablish you, and make you perfect.</hi> Now here they were fulfilling their Ministry for the perfecting of the Saints, that was the worke of their Ministry who had received gifts from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove which were perfect. And here you may see all that the worke of the worlds Ministry is against the worke of the Ministers of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, so making it manifest that they have not their power from God nor Christ, but from him that abode not in the truth, who bring forth no fruit to perfection, as the Pharisees did not. Now saith the Minister of Christ who preached the one offering, saith he, <hi>by one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified;</hi> mark, mind and reade here, <hi>he hath perfected, he hath for ever perfected them that are sanctified, them that are sanctified,</hi> marke againe, <hi>by the one offering.</hi> Now you that be Teachers of the world, which deny perfection and sanctification, and say none shall come to it while they be upon earth, and here the Minister a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Christ saith it, from whom you differ who deny perfection deny the offering and manifest that you are not Saints, but prove your selves to be of him that is out of the truth, Ministers of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.14.</note> not of the Offering which is the righteousnesse; <hi>for whom he hath sanctified he hath perfected for ever them that are sanctified by the one offering.</hi> And here you have proved your selves not to be Ministers of this offering who deny perfection and sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and so in another doctrine then the Apostles were in, and so denyed by the Children of light the Saints, who witnesse the one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168387:5"/>offering which perfects for ever them that are sanctified. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther none see this <hi>Offering</hi> but with the light which from Christ doth come; So you that deny the light, deny the <hi>Offering that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects for ever them that are sanctified,</hi> and you that deny them that are sanctified, deny the one offering which perfects them; so you that deny perfection deny the offering, for that was for the sinnes which the world never owned but hated, which is out of the truth, out of the light; here you manifest your selves to be of the world not of God.</p>
            <p>Againe, You that take tythes doe shew not the Spirit that the Apostles were guided withall, who said the Priesthood was changed that received tithes, and the Law was changed by which it was made, and the Commandement disanuld by which they did take them; so saith the Apostle, <hi>Try the Spirits, and believe not every Sririt, for many false Prophets are gone into the world, which confesse not Christ come in the flesh;</hi> and this is the Antichrist and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver which you have heard spoken off, which now already is in the world, then the Apostle saw them enter into the world. Now that Spirit that tooke ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hes held up the first Priesthood, Temple, and Synagogues, imperfect things, an imperfect Ministry; marke, <hi>which was but a shadow of things that were to come,</hi> that Spirit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed not <hi>Christ come in the flesh,</hi> neither did that Spirit owne the Apostles Spirit that did confesse <hi>Christ come in the flesh,</hi> neither did that Spirit owne the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, but denyed and opposed it, was against it, so Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ which the Apostles which were in the Spirit that confessed <hi>Christ come in the flesh,</hi> which were not of the world, with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they tryed their Spirits which went about to deceive and seduce which he said now already was in the world, were entered in then, therefore he wrote to the Saints to abide in the <hi>Anoynting, which did abide in them, and they needed not that any man teach them, but as the anoynting which they had received from the holy one;</hi> and as these walked in the light they came to have fellowship one with another, and with the Sonne and the Father, and <hi>the blood of Jesus cleansed them from all sinne.</hi> Now the Apostles that were here in the Spirit of Jesus knew the Spirit that went about to deceive and seduce, and that Spirit which was against Christs Spirit Antichrist, and that Prophet which was false, which was out of the light the truth which came from Christ the true Prophet, who saith, <hi>Learne of me I am the way to the Father.</hi> Now he that did not abide in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168387:6"/>the truth, the false Prophets have their power from him, and the seducers and the Antichrists, which the Children of light ever jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and bid them take heed of the <hi>Anoynting</hi> in them, but even as the same anoynting taught them they were to abide therein, which was truth and no lye; And againe, this Spirit said, <hi>try the Spirits,</hi> saw the Spirit that got the forme of godlines, that crept into hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and led people, and they were alwayes learning that followed them, and never were able to come to the knowledge of the truth, being led away with divers lusts, and loaden with sinne, this doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine then crept in, in the dayes of the Apostle <hi>Paul,</hi> and he said, <hi>that they were covetous, and high minded, and heady, traytors, truce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaters, reprobates concerning the faith, which had the forme of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, but denyed the power,</hi> which withstood the truth, as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> did when the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> were to come out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt;</hi> So doe these resist the truth being men of corrupt minds, then their doctrine crept in which is now spread over the world, for such as deny the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, resisteth the truth, as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> did, for the light is the truth, for none come out of the world, but who ownes the light that comes from him, nor none come out of darknesse, and such come to receive the Covenant and the Law written in their hearts, whereby they need no man to teach them, and such see the doctrine the Apostles saw then coming into the world, which now is spread over the world, which are leading people with their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine forty, fifty, sixty, or eighty yeares, <hi>and be alwayes learning, and never able to come to knowledge of the truth, led away with divers lusts, and loaden with sinnes,</hi> and how shall they be ever able to come to knowledge of the truth when their teachers and leaders doe resist the truth, <hi>being men of corrupt minds and reprobate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the faith, which faith gives the victory over the world,</hi> and these teachers which the Apostle saw creeping in then, <hi>which be heady, high-minded, incontinent, fierce, despisers of them that are good,</hi> which are now standing in the world, <hi>leading silly women captive, which be leaden with sinne, and divers lusts, which be alwayes learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and never able to come to knowledge of the truth,</hi> and of whom they learne are Reprobates concerning the faith, which they say while man is upon the earth he shall never be made free from sin, nor never be sanctified, nor never be perfected. So that doctrine crept in then is now standing in the world crying up sinne, so cry up that which is of the Devill, for the Apostle saw that doctrine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168387:6"/>then crept in which did resist the truth, and led people which were alwayes learning, that followed them and were loaden with their sinnes, and such were Reprobates concerning the faith, which resist the light and deny it, but of him which is out of the truth, and what hath he to cry up but sinne? and these are they that lead people al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes captive, and keep them in their sinnes, and which be alwayes learning under them, and never able to come to knowledge of the truth the light which is the truth Christ, but such as come to the knowledge of Christ which is the truth, come to see him that hath given them a light to see their sinnes, he it is that saves them from their sinnes, <hi>whose burthen is light and yoke easie,</hi> and such are they which leade away with lusts as they are which be alwayes <hi>learning and never are able to come to knowledge of the truth;</hi> For the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers them that crept into houses say that men shall never be made free from sinne while upon the earth; and the Apostle said,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note>
               <hi>they were made free from sinne;</hi> and in the Epistle to the <hi>Colossians</hi> saith, <hi>they put off the body of sinne by the Circumcision of the Spirit, and this is the victory over the world, even your faith,</hi> which Christ is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of, which none comes to know the Author of this Faith which gives the victory over the world, which Faith the worlds teachers are reprobate to which gives the victory, but such as own the light which comes from Christ the truth, which light is the truth in the inward parts; and them that lead away with the lusts are led from the light which comes from Christ the Author of the Faith, &amp; that doctrine crept in then, now by the children of light is seene stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the world, which by them is denyed and turned away from, and it can proceed no further, for their folly shall be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest to all men; for as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> which were out of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> light and power with which he saw Christ, them him did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand; so likewise these saith the Apostle <hi>which have the forme of godlines and are crept into houses, which leade silly women captive, which should be alwayes learning and never able to come to knowledge of the truth,</hi> they themselves resisting of it, how can the learner then come to the knowledge of it, when their teachers be reprobate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Faith? and now this is manifested: Now it might have been said to the Apostle, Dost not thou goe into an house? Dost not thou deny the Temple that God Commanded, and teach in thine own hired house the Kingdome of God to all that come to thee? yea the Apostle was in the power of godlines, and the truth, and the substance, and in the Faith, which gives the victory over
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168387:7"/>the world, and saw the other which crept into houses Reprobates concerning the Faith, and resisted the truth, though they had the forme of godlines, which kept people alwayes learning, which cry now against perfection, against sanctification, against overcoming of sinne, and so are against the Faith that gives the victory and the offering, against the truth that makes free, which truth thousands do witnesse and are come to the knowledge off &amp; learne of, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one doe till they come to the light which comes from him the Author of the Faith, &amp; here they receive the power from on high, but them that resist the truth are against the light and receive not it, which Christ hath enlightened every one that cometh into the world withall, and such are Reprobates concerning the Faith, and receive not the power, but are such as may get the forme, and so keepe people alwayes learning, loaden with their sinnes and divers lusts, which led them captive, but this is manifested with the light and judged, which leads people and are alwayes learning, but shall never come to knowledge of the truth, and turne people to the light they are enlightened withall, which comes from Christ the truth, to learne of him that they might come out of captivity, for that which keepes people alwayes learning and from the truth, <hi>which are never able to come to the knowledge of it, and leads them captive loaden with sinnes and divers lusts, and they themselves getting the forme of godlines, which are covetous, traitors, heady, high-minded, and selfe-wild, living in pleasure, such which resist the truth, men of corrupt mindes, Reprobates concerning the Faith, and all led captive,</hi> these are Ministers of Sathan not of God, they be all contrary to the light, which be in all those things before mentioned, as <hi>trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, heady, high-minded, truce-breakers, incontinent, fierce, dispisers, lovers of pleasure more then lovers of God.</hi> Now this is all manifest to be out of the truth which the Apostle spake of, of him that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode not in it, so condemned by them that do abide in it &amp; judged and condemned who be in the truth in the Faith, for these are they that have kept people and doe keep people till they be 30, 40, 50, or 60 yeares learning, and are never able to come to knowledge of the truth, for the teachers themselves doe resist it, and be reprobate concerning the Faith, and these are the Antichrists which <hi>John</hi> saw enter into the world, for he is an Antichrist that is against the light of Christ, and he is a false teacher that is against the light of Christ, and a false Prophet is against the light, and such are they that get the forme of godlines being Reprobates concerning the faith, for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168387:7"/>none sees faith but with the light of Christ, who is the Author of it. And these are them the Apostle saw then did resist the truth which past over the world, which now are seene and manifested to be them which kept people alwayes learning, which be Reprobates concerning the Faith, who resisteth the truth, the light, which ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth every man that cometh into the world with all their strength stand against it, and these are them which leade people so long captive, who have gotten the forme of godlines, but deny the power which power now denyes them.</p>
            <p>And the Teachers of the world now standing in the world, which are of it, make the blood of Jesus Christ of none effect &amp; say, while they be upon the earth, they shall not have their sinnes all washed away, sin is of the Devill, which appeare to be Ministers of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, so here is a giving liberty to the Devill, and a place for him, when the Apostle saith, <hi>Give not place to the Devill,</hi> who saith, <hi>that the blood of Christ Jesus cleanseth from all sinne, and you are washed, you are sanctified, and made white and cleane through the blood of the Lambe, who purchased to himselfe a Church without spot or wrinkle or blemish, or any such thing;</hi> this was the Ministers of Christs testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of him, his Church, his blood, which is contrary to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters testimony of the world, who deny and say they shall not be cleansed from their sinnes while they be upon the earth, &amp; so are them which make the <hi>blood of Christ of none effect,</hi> for the blood of the first Covenant was for the cleansing, but did not make perfect, for it was not possible it should take away all sin; so here you may see where they be, not of the second Covenant. And you bring this Scripture, <hi>If we say we have no sinne, we deceive our selves, and the truth is not in us,</hi> he that saith he hath not sinned makes him a liar, if he had not sinned, what need he a Saviour to save him from it? <hi>and the blood of Jesus cleanseth from it;</hi> but mind, <hi>if you confesse your sinnes, he is faithfull and j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st to forgive, and the blood of Jesus Christ cleanseth from all sinne;</hi> so here is a time of seeing sinne a time of confessing, and a time of forsaking, and a witnessing the blood of Jesus that cleanseth from all sinne; here the Children of light come to know the effect of it, &amp; they that made the blood of Jesus Christ of none effect and doe now, are them that are covetous, which be in the Idolatry, pleading for sin not for the blood which cleanseth from all sin, which are the covetous, as <hi>Jude</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> speakes off, that goe in <hi>Cains</hi> way, and <hi>Balaams</hi> way, have erred from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and the Commands of God, which teacheth your owne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168387:8"/>for doctrine, which keepes you from the light which gives you to know Christs Commands and his doctrine; So you that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the <hi>blood of Jesus to cleanse you from all sinne,</hi> you are them that deny the light which brings you to see and confesse it, which light waiting in it you come to see the blood of Jesus that cleanseth from the sin that light lets you see, which the Children of light witness. So you that be the teachers of the world, which be out of the truth of him that abode not in it, doe give the ignorant people <hi>Davids</hi> tremblings, quakings prophesies, prayings and fastings in meeter to sing, and for them doe call God to witnesse, <hi>that they are not puft in mind, nor have no scornfull eye,</hi> this is given by you in meeter to the world, to them that be out of the truth, &amp; out of understanding among the mockers, scoffers persecutors, haling out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues shewing a Cage of uncleane birds, that the Spirit speaks off that gave forth Scripture, and shewing how you doe sing with a Spirit, but not with the Spirit of understanding, but that which is out of truth; so not come to know <hi>Davids</hi> condition, for he was scoffed at, with the scorners, reproachers, &amp; mockers, when those conditions were given forth from the Spirit, which now is turned into meeter, &amp; you that be out of the truth sing, but not with that Spirit that gave them forth, and so you that deny the Light which comes from Christ the Saviour of the world, who hath enlightened every one that cometh into the world, you deny the blood, for <hi>i.</hi> you that deny the light that enlightens every man that cometh into the world, you deny that which shews a man sin &amp; himselfe, which after a man sees sin and himselfe, he waites for the blood of Jesus to cleanse him from all sin which his Light gives him to see, &amp; here you are out of the way the doctrine of the Apostles, and not of the truth but of him that was out of it, and so of the Lord Jesus Christ no Ministers but of the unrighteous, for none ownes the blood but such as own the light which gives to see that which is out of truth and doth it condemne; here all you that be out of truth and light are condemned with the light who are out of the truth, which be of him that is out of the truth and abide not in it. And so you that be out of the truth deny the light, and are of him that abode not in it, who deny the blood of Christ to cleanse you from all sinne, so of Christ no Ministers, but of him that abode not in the truth.</p>
            <p>And againe, you that are called Ministers of the world, which owne not the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, that doe not believe in it, but make a scoffe at the light
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168387:8"/>within, and so have cleared your selves from that light within that shines in the heart, and of that knowledge which the light gives, which is to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ, which was the end of the Apostles Ministry to bring them to the light that shined in their hearts, and to turne them from darknesse to the light, that they might come to that which gives them the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ: So all you teachers which be out of the light and truth, which deny this light within, which is to give this knowledge, you be in another knowledge, and come not to see the glory of God, but doe manifest whose Ministers you are who deny the light within, so keep people from that which should give them the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ, which the Ministers of Christ seeke to bring to, so manifest your selves to be in darknesse and of him that abode not in the truth, judged and seene by the Children of light.</p>
            <p>And againe, you Ministers of the world which deny the light which lighteth every one that cometh into the world, you are them which teach the people lyes and tell them the declaration is the word, when as the Ministers of the word said that which they set forth was a Declaration, and call it a Treatise, and call it a declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and said God was the Word &amp; the Word became flesh, which none know the Word that became flesh and Christ the light, but such who owned the light that he l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghted them withall, and these were not Ministers of the Letter but of the Spirit, but the Ministers of the world say, that the declaration is the light and the word, contrary to Scripture, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. <hi>Acts</hi> 1. Here the Ministers of Satan which are out of the truth and abode not in it, he and his Ministers, Messengers, Prophets, Teachers and Apostles, may and doe get the declaration the Scriptures, and the forme, and call them the light, and them the word, and deny the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, which cometh from Christ the word, for he it is that doth torment him to overthrow his kingdome; So to deceive the world S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tans Ministers and Teachers and Prophets and Apostles, may get the declaration, the Scripture, and call it the light, and it the word, and so speake a lye, for he speakes of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, when the Ministers of the word said, Christ was the light and G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> so he speakes a lye, who speakes of his owne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his word, and knows the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and God is the word, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168387:9"/>Christ is the light which lighteth every one that cometh into the world, this his Ministers declare in their Declaration, and they said Christ his name was called the word of God, and not the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they did not say that was his name, but the false Prophets and the Deceivers have given it the name of Christ, so not suffering them to owne the light which should leade them out of their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and such as contrad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct their false doctrine have many been cast into prison by the Devill to be tryed.</p>
            <p>And againe, the Teachers of the world which deny the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, say that the Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-house is the Church, and so with the light which cometh from him by whom the world was made, they are seene to be of him who abode not in the truth, for the Ministers of Christ said the Church was in God the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ which was the pillar and ground of truth, and the Church of Christ is without spot or wrinkle or blemish, or any such thing, and in it saith the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of Christ the Prophets might speake two or three and the rest might judge, and if any thing was revealed to him that sate by, let the first hold his peace, for you may all speake one by one, that all may learne &amp; all may be comforted; the Spirit of the Prophets was subject to the Prophets, for God was not the Author of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion but of peace, and this Order was in the Church of God. Now in the Church of the world which is the Steeple-house, this Order of the Church is denyed, and that which comforts in the Church of Christ is denyed, whereby all might learne which is in the Church of Christ, but denyed in the worlds Church, and that which is peace and tends to edification in the Church of Christ, is confusion in the Church of the world, &amp; sets them all in distracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whose Spirits are not subject to the Spirit of the Prophets; so their Ministry is found here out of the steps of the Apostles, whose Ministry is limited to a glasse, which was not the Apostles, so here their Church is contrary, their Ministry is contrary, their practice is contrary proved by Scripture, there is not the learning, nor the edification as in the Church of the Saints. And againe, when any have been moved to come into the Church in the world, they have been all on heaps to speake, knocking them downe, the Priests have said, take them away Magistrate; here they are them that doe quench the Spirit, which the Ministers of Christ said, <hi>quench not,</hi> here they are them that goe about to limit the holy one, which the Prophets did not, but the Apostle saith, <hi>You may speake one by one,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168387:9"/>that all may learne, and all may be comforted;</hi> and here you may see they are contrary to the Prophets, the Apostles, and the Scriptures, and the Spirit that gave them forth, and so that Priesthood which did not owne Christ who lighteth every man that cometh into the world, was of him who is out of the truth, and so with clubs and staves and swords the multitude had Authority from the chiefe Priests to persecute the light, as now the teachers of the world with clubs and staves and stones doe the multitude rise against the truth, having their authority from the chiefe Priests, who call to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, stand up for the Gospel, and then the people fall a fighting and persecuting and plucking by the haire of the head, and haling out of the Synagogues and before Rulers &amp; casting into prison. Now peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple mark, are not these wolves? the fruits of them which Christ said he did send his sheep among? was ever Christs lambs or his Church guarded with clubs and with staves? and caused them to be cast in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to prison when any came to them and spit upon them? Did the lambes ever rise with clubs and staves and the sheepe against any? are not these ill savours among them that are called Christians? which the lambes never practised the Ministers of Christ. But doth not this shew the chiefe Priests authority, and doe not you fulfill it in this age against the Lambs, of whom Christ saith, <hi>I send you forth as lambs among wolves?</hi> are not these the fruits of wolves, tearing, rending, devouring, mocking, scoffing, prisoning persecuting, whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, mis-naming, slandering, and reproaching? and doth not this shew the fruit of them that be out of the truth without the feare of God? and hath not this proved you to be those Prophets that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> speakes off, <hi>that by their lyes and lightnes had not profited the people at all?</hi> doth not this now give an ill savour &amp; smell? therefore saith he, <hi>hearken not to them, though wisdome cry in the streets, &amp; the beginning of it is the feare of God, which feare of God is to depart from sinne and evill.</hi> Now here is the beginning of wisdome, and <hi>this wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome crys in the streets, her maidens are gone forth in the highest place of the Citty, who is simple let him turne in hither; As for him that wants understanding she saith to him come, forsake foolishnes and live,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 9.</note>
               <hi>goe into the way of understanding.</hi> And the teachers of the world that deny the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world say, that Hebrew, Greek, &amp; Latine is the Originall, and such as have this originall are the orthodox men to open the Scriptures; and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> which knew not Christ the light, but crucified him, when that he had crucified him he wrote a superscription in Hebrew, Greeke,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168387:10"/>and Latine, and set that over him, and them that had the Hebrew Greeke, and Latine knew not Christ but crucified him; And saith, <hi>Moses, All the earth was of one Language before Babel and Nimrod the cunning hunter before the Lord whose kingdome was the beginning of Babel, whom God did confound into many Languages.</hi> Now you may see <hi>Pilate</hi> had these Languages and crucified Christ, which the Ministers of the world say is the originall, and they and their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall is stopt at <hi>Babel</hi> &amp; can goe no farther, and so bewitch the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and all people that be kept under them and their Originall are stopt at <hi>Babel,</hi> and they that had that Originall crucified Christ. Now here we see that they are not come so far as <hi>Moses,</hi> who saw before <hi>Babel</hi> was, and the many languages which is the worlds ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, where the world and their originall is stopt at <hi>Babel.</hi> So now they being in <hi>Babylon</hi> the many languages building up &amp; throwing downe, not owning the light which came from Christ the Word which was in the beginning before the world was, with which light the word came to be seene, which was before <hi>Babel</hi> was &amp; <hi>Nimrod</hi> and the languages were and <hi>Pilate</hi> was, &amp; the worlds originall, and with the light which comes from the word see all the worlds tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and originall stopt at <hi>Babel,</hi> and the people that are kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their originall and doctrine, &amp; so there they deceive them, and they can goe no farther than <hi>Babel,</hi> for all the earth was of one lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage before &amp; <hi>Pilate</hi> was as wise as you are which crucified Christ who had the languages which is your originall. Therfore every one of you having a light from Christ the word which was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before the many languages were, with the light come to see the word which was in the beginning; here a <hi>Peter</hi> or a <hi>John</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned in the letter, receiving the word he shal know the scripture, he shall receive the power of God, which they that doe not owne the light, though they be learned in all the languages &amp; great Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Rabbies know not the Scripture nor Christ, untill they owne the light, but are they that are stopt at <hi>Babel;</hi> For saith the worlds teachers unlearned men &amp; unstable doe wrest the Scripture to their owne destruction, <hi>Peter</hi> said so who was an unlearned man in the letter, but he knew the Scripture being learned of Christ the word, And the Scribes and Pharisees which were learned men in the Scripture, and teachers and guides, but did not see the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, these were they that knew not Scripture nor Christ the substance; &amp; here you may see what the learning was that <hi>Peter</hi> speakes off, who was an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168387:10"/>man, and what the worlds originall is which is stopt at <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> and can goe no farther; the Children of light which are in the light which comes from the word from the beginning, comprehend and see the worlds doctrine here to be stopt at <hi>Babel,</hi> so here is the body of confusion <hi>Babel</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> where the mother of harlots is harlots mark from the word, from the light, for who come to the word, come to the light and see before <hi>Babel</hi> was, and <hi>Babylon,</hi> and are brought out of it; So come over all the worlds teachers, they that walke in the light &amp; reacheth to the light in every man which he hates, and they are the light of the world, &amp; the salt of the earth, and now is the Lord gathering together his elect &amp; chosen his roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all seed which his promise is too, but all those that are contrary to the light and in <hi>Babylon</hi> the mother of the harlots stopt at <hi>Babel,</hi> and tell the world that is the Originall, they are all with the light cut out and condemned that contrary to it doe act, who are out of the truth and teach lyes which is not of the truth, but of the Devill who abode not in the truth, where confusion, distraction &amp; distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is, all that with the light is seene and condemned from the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that be of the light, in which they have unity &amp; peace out of all confusion, so are on the top of that the world call the originall, and before it was in the light, with which they see Christ reigne, him that <hi>Moses</hi> spake off, who said, <hi>all the earth was of one language before Babel.</hi> Now you may see all the worlds teachers traced and their steps out of <hi>Moses,</hi> out of Christ, and the Apostles, in the steps of them that crucified him, who cry up that to be the Originall, the superscription that was set over Christ, but God is now taking off their covers, now the blindnes of the peoples eyes and the scales be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to fall from their eyes, that they shall not be bewitched nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no longer by such as teach lyes, who are of him that abode not in the truth, for such are his.</p>
            <p>And the teachers of the world which owne not the light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world say, the 4 bookes, <hi>Mathew, Mark, Luke</hi> &amp; <hi>John</hi> is the Gospell, and many that heard Christs words outwardly and those foure bookes outwardly know not the Gospel, <hi>which is the power of God unto salvation to every one that doth believe,</hi> and the Gospel was preached to <hi>Abraham</hi> in the dayes of old before the 4 books were written, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3 3. but now we see in whom the God of this world hath blinded the minds, mark in whom, <hi>of them which believe not, least the light of the glorious Gospel of Christ, who is the image of God should shine unto them, for we preach
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168387:11"/>not our selves, but Christ Jesus the Lord, and our selves servants for your sakes, for God who commanded light to shine out of darknes, hath shined in our hearts to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ, and this treasure we have in earthen vessells.</hi> Now, where the light that shines in the heart out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God is not seene nor owned, the God of the world hath blinded their minds that the light of the glorious Gospel they see not. So now all you teachers of the world that deny the Light which Christ Jesus doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world withall &amp; see not it, the God of the world hath blinded your minds, and so you are seeking for the earth first, <hi>and what you shall eate, and what you shall drinke, and what you shall put on, and how much or what you may have a yeare,</hi> are out of Christs doctrine and Command, who saith, <hi>Seeke the kingdome of God first, and the righteousnes of it, &amp; all these things will follow;</hi> so the <hi>ravens</hi> here stand up as Judge against you, the <hi>lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the field</hi> they are Judge upon you, and <hi>the grasse which to day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to morrow is cast into the Oven, for after such things the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the world sought,</hi> which shews that you are not out of them; So the Gospel here is <hi>the power of God unto salvatihn unto every one that doth believe,</hi> &amp; he that believeth in the light which enlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every man that cometh into the world, he that believeth here and receiveth the light receiveth Christ <hi>and shall have power yea to become the Sonnes of God,</hi> shall receive power which is the Gospell, <hi>and he that believeth here shall never dye, nor come into Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor be confounded,</hi> for he believeth in that which manifesteth that which is to be confounded, nor be ashamed, for he beliveth in that which manifests that which is contrary to the light which who acts in there comes the shame.</p>
            <p>The worlds teachers that be out of truth tell you, that they thresh in hope, and plough in hope, that they may be made pertakers of their hope, and they thresh it may be 40 yeares, 50 yeares, and 60 yeares, and plough it may be so long too, and when they have done are faine to seeke to the Magistrates for meanes. And againe, they say he that plants a vineyard is to eate the fruite of it, and some it may be plant 40, 50, or 60 yeares, and when they have done they are faine to seeke to the Magistrate for meanes, or sue people at the Law, which was not the practice of the Apostles, these are them that beate the aire, and they will tell people <hi>that the labourer is worthy of his hire, and the workman is worthy of his meate,</hi> such as never hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168387:11"/>neither did set them at worke, and if they will not give them what they demand, which neither set them at work nor hired them, send for writts for them and sue them at the Law, and bring the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles words for their Cloake, who be out of the truth; if they will not give them what they doe desire, and say <hi>the workman is worthy of his meate, and the labourer of his hire.</hi> Now these are the Ministers of unrighteousnes, for here they make themselves manifest, whether these be righteous Ministers let all that be in the truth judge, and are fit to teach people, whose selfe thus appeares, who be out of the light, and out of righteousnes and equity, and out of the truth; so I would have all to consider, for God will measure your wayes, and weigh your actions with his ballance, and who are found too light and too short, consider your portion, for to man you may flatter, but Gods kingdome is not wonne so, who will bring your workes to the light.</p>
            <p>And them which be the worlds teachers, &amp; not sent of Christ out of his way and doctrine, sprinkle Infants and teach it for doctrine and say it is a command of Christ, the which Christ never comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; For first saith he, <hi>goe teach,</hi> and then <hi>disciple or baptize, and repent and be baptized,</hi> it is a changeing of the minde out of that where it hath been, and turning it to Christ, which makes a disciple one with that in <hi>Mat:</hi> 28. The teachers of the world sprinkle their Infants, which they call their <hi>Baptisme,</hi> and preach to them after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance it may be 20 or 30 yeares after, so having not a Cōmand from Christ to doe what they practice, they preach up their owne commands for doctrine, as it was in the dayes of Christ in the flesh, they that did not believe in him taught for doctrine the Cōmands of men, such as were out of the life of <hi>Moses,</hi> the life of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the life of Christ. And now such as be out of the life of Christ, the Prophets, and the Apostles, doe the same they teach for doctrine the Commands of men, which the children of light cannot owne, neither Commands nor doctrine, who owne Christ, who learne of him and know his doctrine and his Commandements. And further they tell of a Sacrament, for which there is no Scripture, and them that be out of the light are imitating something about that, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the darke are fighting and destroying one another about it, and so would have the likenes of the Lords Supper, which is often a dinner in their time of dinner, which Christ gave to his disciples at night, but the Children of light witnesse the Supper of the Lord which differeth them from all the world, &amp; the imitation of a thing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168387:12"/>without life and power, taken up as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did their Sacrifices and Commands, which knew not the substance of what they acted, neither doe these now who are destroying one another about sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, which hate the light, and believe not in it, which gives to see the body which is Christ.</p>
            <p>And againe, the teachers that be of the world made by the will of man, sent out by man, they have their two mother-schools, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they have the heathenish Authors, &amp; the traditions of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, so these which are the two schooles, which they call the two Mothers, which they call the two Fountaines, such teachers as are come from them made by the will of man not by the will of God, deny the light w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> lighteth every man that cometh into the world, so themselves are kept from the fountaine of mercy, and God the fountaine of all good, and Christ the treasury of wisdome &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for none come to see this treasure of wisdome &amp; knowledge, but who owne the light which Christ hath given them, and this light is contrary to the will of man, &amp; so the teachers of the world themselves being kept from the light, not owning it, keep all people from the light, and so the Cisternes that hold not the living mercies, which light they receive not though they be enlightened, and so keepe all from it, in which light the Children of light walke, which they keepe people from, and these are the wolves &amp; greedy doggs that have never enough that <hi>Isaiah</hi> speakes off, which are guarded with clubs and staves &amp; goales, and they hate the light, with which light the children of light see the Lord is drying up their fountaines and their springs, and their rivers and their pooles, and <hi>makes their fruitfull field a wildernes, a place for dragons, and their Cage a place for uncleane Spirits, and now the howling of every uncleane Spirit is heard, and the fenced Citty shall be laid desolate, and the songs of the temple be turned into howling, the Citty of confusion is brought downe and shall be brought downe; come out of Babylon, remove out of the midst of Babylon and goe forth, for the Lord will raise and cause to come against Babylon an Assembly of great Nations from the North Countrey, they shall set themselves in array against her, and their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes shall be as of a mighty expert man, none shall returne in vaine; Oh you destroyers of mine heritage, because you are growne fatt as the heifer at grasse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 50</note>
               <hi>and bellow as bulls;</hi> marke, <hi>your mother shall be sore confounded, she that bare you shall be ashamed;</hi> marke and reade.</p>
            <p>And the called teachers of the world which be in envie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, get the Apostles words and say, <hi>Some doe preach Christ out
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168387:12"/>of envie, and some doe preach Christ of good will, and some doe preach Christ out of contention and strife, though they adde affliction to his bonds,</hi> &amp; in this preaching the Apostle rejoyced, &amp; here is a cloake for all the envious teachers and contentious teachers, and such tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers that live in strife; that was a time when few did believe there was a Christ; so for the spreading of Christs name abroad, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle suffered such teachers before mentioned, envious, contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and such that were in strife, but when Christs name was spread abroad the Apostle said, <hi>Shun the occasion of men of strife,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.9. Rom. 13. 2 Tim. 3.</note>
               <hi>and vaine contentions and envious ones, for they had not so learned Christ, and he that had the forme of godlines &amp; not the power turne away from such;</hi> so though there was a time that he suffered that which they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to <hi>adde affliction to his bonds,</hi> and there was a time he againe trampled upon, when Christs name was spread abroad, and many had got the forme of godlinesse and not the power, which he bids <hi>turne away from.</hi> And the Apostle bid the Saints <hi>put on the armour of light, and not to walke in strife nor envie,</hi> and bid them <hi>avoid such Questions as ingender to strife and prophane &amp; vaine bablings,</hi> which increaseth ungodlines and contention and strife avoid, &amp; before he rejoyced in such that <hi>preached Christ out of envie &amp; strife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> and this is the teachers of the worlds cloake, who be out of the <hi>armour of light,</hi> which the Apostle bid the Saints put on, but all that be in the light may see their cloake will not cover them, and they have not the understanding of the Apostles doctrine, but with it judged, &amp; by the Apostles spirit people are commanded to <hi>turne away from them,</hi> though for a time he suffered such, though they <hi>added affliction to his bonds;</hi> so each of the times the Apostle speakes off is seene with them that be in the light, and these turned from, that he speakes off, that be in the strife and envie and contention, which onely have gotten the words, but are found out of the light and life that gave them forth; and the Children of light do see that they be not in the Spirit that gave forth the Scripture, which be in the strife and the envie, so from them are turned with the light, which will reach to the light in every one, which will be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of them that hate it, and to you this is the word of the Lord, therefore repent for the Lord is awakening that of his owne in every man, they shall heare the voice of his Sonne, for the Lord is drawing to him.</p>
            <p>And the teachers of the world for their going into the Temple &amp; Synagogues, as they call it, bring this for their cloake that Christ
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168387:13"/>went into the Temple, and the Apostles went into the Synagogues, this the teachers of the world bring for their cloake for their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, who have 100 <hi>l.</hi> or 20, or more or lesse as they can agree with people: Now the Apostles and Christs going into Temple and Synagogues, Christ went in to fullfill that w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> was written of him, and to shew the fulfilling of it, so that which was written in the Prophets and the Law might be fulfilled, &amp; the Apostles and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples going into Synagogues among the chiefe Priests, Pharisees, and the Doctors, which had <hi>Moses</hi> &amp; the Prophets and read them every Sabbath day, the Disciples and Apostles shewed them out of the Prophets and <hi>Moses</hi> which they read that Jesus was the Christ, for the Prophets prophesied of the coming of the just one, &amp; <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> wrote of him and said, <hi>Like unto me will God raise up a Prophet, him the people should heare.</hi> Now the Apostles going into the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues was to shew this Prophet, and the fulfilling of the Prophets and <hi>Moses</hi> words, and their portion in Synagogue and Temple was haling out, and Christ spake unto them of it, <hi>that they should be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out, and that they should scourge them there,</hi> which the Apostles found fulfilled, and so the Apostles and Disciples which Christ sent forth, which went into the temple and villages and townes, did not goe to agree with them for so much a yeare to stay in their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, but Christ who came to fulfill what was written of him in the Law and the Prophets, sent his Disciples and Apostles forth, and gave them power and sent them into the villages, townes, temple, and Synagogues, and they shewed out of the Scripture to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>that Jesus was the Christ.</hi> Now the <hi>Bereans</hi> they searched the Prophets,
<note place="margin">Acts 17.</note> whether the things were so or not the Apostle spoke, and the <hi>Thessalonians</hi> they fell a persecuting, so the <hi>Bereans</hi> were more noble that searched than they that persecuted, &amp; Christ sent forth his Disciples and Apostles here freely without a bag or scrip or silver in their purses; <hi>into what house you enter say peace be in this house, and there abide, and what they set before you that eate, asking no Question, freely you have received, freely give.</hi> Now this agrees with the Apostles words, who said, <hi>if we minister unto you spirituall things, it is the least if we reape of you carnall, for thou shalt not muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the Corne.</hi> And the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which freely were to give, who had freely received, did minister spirituall things and so they <hi>were to eate what was set before them,</hi> and he said to them <hi>the workman is worthy of his meate, and the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beurer of his hire,</hi> they were not to agree with the people of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168387:13"/>Synagogue, or Towne, for tithe or 100 <hi>l.</hi> or more or lesse, or else they would not stay, as the worlds teachers doe now where they can light of a bigger Benefice, they have a call thither; so Christs Ministers had not a call to great Benefices, which Ministers that ministred spirituall things were to eate of their carnall, was agreeable to the Apostles words, who said, <hi>If one minister unto you spirituall things, it is the least that we should receive of your carnall,</hi> though he said <hi>he coveted no mans silver nor gold nor apparell, though he thus spake.</hi> And the first Priesthood that tooke the tithes perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the Apostles and Disciples from Citty to Citty, that held up synagogues and Temple, who preached Christ the second Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood the end of the first Priesthood that tooke tithes. Now say the Teachers of the world they deny the Temple which God had commanded, making themselves ignorant of the Scriptures and of the power of God, for though God did Command the Temple, <hi>Solomon</hi> was to build him an house so long building, and so many builders of it, and when it was built its time it was to be a house of prayer, and when Christ came, who said, <hi>a greater then Solomon was here,</hi> he went into the Temple, cleansed the Temple, whipt them out, the buyers and sellers, and said, <hi>his Fathers house ought to be a house of prayer, but they had made it a denne of thieves; And when he was come out of the Temple, he came upon the Mount, and his Disciples came to him and shewed him the building of the Temple, and he said unto them it was to be throwne downe and not one stone left upon another.</hi> And <hi>Stephen</hi> for witnessing against the Temple was stoned to death, and witnessing Christ the substance. And <hi>Paul</hi> was haled out of the Temple, who went into it to shew to people Christ the substance, and them that did not believe held up the Temple, and the first Priesthood Pharisees and Scribes that tooke tithes and paid tithes, and them that did believe in Christ Jesus a greater then <hi>Solomon</hi> that built the Temple, these came to witnesse him before figures and shadowes were, and the end of all figures, types, and shadowes, the summe and substance of all whose bodies were made the Temples of God, and these were them that wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed Christ, who were haled out of the Temple and Synagogues by them that held them up, and by them they were tortured and imprisoned and whipt and beate, as in this age the Generation of men that be out of the light that comes from Christ, who be in the stepps of them that persecuted the Apostles which were in the light, which they now persecute them that be in the same light,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168387:14"/>and witnesse Christ <hi>the same yesterday to day and for ever,</hi> the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of all and the summe of all figures which none sees but such who believe in the light that comes from him, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> they that hate it and doe not owne it are with it condemned, though they may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse all the Scriptures, reade this with the light that gave it forth, and then you will see with that what is out of truth and what is in the truth, and come to discover truth from error, the Ministers of Sathan from the Ministers of Christ, of righteousnesse from unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse. So the Lord open your understandings, for he is come to reigne and will be magnified in his Saints, who is the glory of <hi>Israel,</hi> who lighteth every man that cometh into the world, thou that hatest it and lovest it not, this will be thy Condemnation and believest not in it, but he that believeth shall not be condemned, but he that doth not believe he it is that is condemned, and he it is that will not have Christ to reigne over him, as the <hi>Jewes</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors now which talke of Christs words, but will not have him to reigne over them, who lighteth every one of them that cometh into the world, that through him they might believe, here they professe his words, but will not owne his light which comes from Christ, from him to governe them who is the King of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> whose Scepter is a righteous Scepter, who now takes his kingdome to whom the glory belongs, &amp; the riches of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> is brought; whose Fathers have killed the Apostles and Martyrs, and they build their Sepulchers, as the Fathers of the Pharisees kild the Prophets, and they built their Sepulchers.
<note place="margin">Isa. 19.</note> But the Lord shall be made knowne to <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> shall be made knowne to the Lord, whom the Lord of Hoasts shall blesse, saying, <hi>Blessed be Egypt my people, and Assyria the worke of my hands, and Israel mine inhehitance.</hi> And all in the light dwell that you may see what is out of the light, out of the truth, and is with the light condemned; now you have time prize it, this is the day of your visitation, least you say your time is past; the rich gluttons time was past, when he was in the lake. <hi>Esau</hi> had lost his time, despised his birth-right, <hi>and afterwards sought it with teares, but no place was found for repentance. Pharaoh</hi> saw his sinne and confessed it when the plagues were upon him, and when they were off remained in the hardnesse of his heart, untill God overthrew him and destroyed him. <hi>Herod</hi> sought to destroy the Saints, and at last the Angel of the Lord smote him. And <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> lost his Kingdome, who tooke the people captive, who would have had them bow to his image, which they could
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168387:14"/>not, he it was that lost his Kingdome. <hi>Cain</hi> had a promise before he was a vagabond, but now <hi>Cain</hi> is seene that doth not well, who hath not an habitation in God; and prophane <hi>Esau,</hi> the hidden things of him are found, for the day is made manifest, so he was prophane that sought to slay <hi>Jacob,</hi> and he was in envie that sought to slay <hi>Abell,</hi> and <hi>Ishmael</hi> was cast out that was the mocker and the scoffer at the Sonne of the free-woman; and <hi>Herod</hi> he was the persecutor that the Angel of the Lord smote, and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> tooke the Children of God captive, who lost his kingdome, and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that was a task-master, cruell oppressor &amp; proud, though by times he did confesse his sinne, yet not it forsooke, God did him destroy and overthrew in the Sea; and proud <hi>Haman</hi> the Children of the Lord God which to him could not bow, he would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed them all, against whom the Lords hand was turned and destroyed him. You that be in these stepps, consider your exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; Many of the teachers before mentioned of the world were the Bishops flatterers, and they held them up untill they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, and the Kings flatterers untill he was destroyed, therefore hearken to the Lord all people, take warning for these were the branches of trees, least any of these branches be grafted into you, and God turne his hand against you, and plucke you up but every one keepe to the light that comes from Christ, that you may know his Government &amp; come under his Government that hath no end, and learne of Christ, that you may be grafted into him; And every one of you having a light from Christ, being turned to the light that comes from Christ, will learne of Christ, if you be ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand of thousands, one light, one way, one truth, one head, many members, yet one body, whom Christ governeth with his power, for by him were all things created.</p>
            <p>And the teachers of the world for their standing in the Pulpits bring <hi>Ezra's</hi> standing in the Pulpit and reading the Law in the old time, these are the false teachers of the world, but saith the true teacher of Christ Jesus the end of the Law, who told the people the <hi>Lord would write his Law in their hearts, and put it into their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, and heare it from the Lord,</hi> and here is the end of <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra's</hi> Pulpit, and the false teachers cloake taken off, and they are found naked and not in the stepps of <hi>Ezra</hi> who had the Law to reade, and here themselves not Ministers of Christ, who is the end of the Law for righteousnesse sake, which the Ministers of Christ preached, which established the Law, and said, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> write the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168387:15"/>Law in their hearts,</hi> and this comes now to be seene by the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light who are called out from the Children of darknesse and the Deceivers that be in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cain</hi> was the first birth in the transgression, and the sacrifice of the first birth God accepted not, but the sacrifice of the second birth God had respect to, and the first slew the second. And <hi>Noah a preacher of righteousnesse, the eighth person found favour with God,</hi> marke, <hi>a preacher of righteousnesse, a just and an upright man in his time, walked with God, the earth also was corrupt before God, the earth was fild with cruelty, and God looked upon the earth and behold it was corrupt, for all flesh had corrupted its way upon the earth.</hi> And God drowned the old world, and saved <hi>Noah a preacher of righteousnesse, the eight person,</hi> and setting them forth an example to all that after them should live ungodly. And <hi>Abraham</hi> begate <hi>Isaack</hi> and <hi>Ishmael</hi> was the first borne, who was a wild man and a scoffer, who was cast forth. And <hi>Isack</hi> begate <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Esau,</hi> and to <hi>Isack</hi> the promise was, and <hi>Esau</hi> was the first, a prophane person, despised his birth-right, a cunning hunter, a man of the Field, became a place for Dragons, and sought to slay <hi>Jacob</hi> to whom there was no place of repentance found, but <hi>Jacob</hi> was a plaine and a perfect man and dwelled in tents. And in the dayes of the true Prophets there were <hi>Baals</hi> Prophets whom God did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found which were false. And in the dayes of <hi>Jeremy</hi> there were the Priests that he witnessed against, which held up the horrible filthy thing committed in the Land. And in the dayes of the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Isaiah</hi> there were the false Shepheards that sought for the gaine from their Quarter, the greedy dumbe doggs. And in the dayes of <hi>Ezechiel</hi> there were the false Shepheards that sought for the fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce and devoured and killed them that were fed, from whose mouthes the Lord said <hi>he would deliver his sheepe, and feed them himselfe upon the topps of the mountaines.</hi> And in the dayes of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> there were the false teachers and Priests, such as preached for hire and divined for money, for which cause they brought <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to be in heapes, and <hi>Sion</hi> to be plowed up like a field, and the house of the Lord to be like a forrest, and if they did not put into their mouthes they bit them with their teeth, these teachers and Prophets did whom God said <hi>night should come upon them and they should cover their lips, and had no Answer from God.</hi> And in the dayes of Christ there was the multitude of blind guides, hypocrites, Serpents, whited walls, built the tombes of the Prophets and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:168387:15"/>who professed his words but in the hypocrisie out of the life of <hi>Moses</hi> &amp; the Prophets, against the life who was Christ. And in the dayes of <hi>John</hi> there were them that rejected his Councell which to themselves brought destruction. In the dayes of <hi>Moses</hi> there were them that stood against him <hi>Jannes</hi> &amp; <hi>Jambres</hi> resisting the truth, which truth is the light. And in the dayes of the true Apostles there were false Apostles, and the false teachers and the seducers and the deceivers, which got the forme of godlines, but had not the power, and the Antichrist which then the Apostle saw these came in which are now past over the world, crying against the Ministers of Christ and of God, which preach Christ the one offering, by which they that are sanctified are perfected; marke, they that are sanctified, he doth not say shall be but are pefected for ever, doth not say shall be which the Deceiver saith not, here we prove you whose Ministers you are; And God gave gifts unto men and the gifts that he gave were perfect, &amp; every gift that proceeds from God is perfect, and these gifts that he gave unto men were for the Ministers worke, and they were to perfect the Saints, this Ministry was for the perfecting of the Saints, &amp; these gifts they were to minister according to their gifts they were to impart their gifts, &amp; that gift which they were to impart was perfect, so that which they were to minister which was for the perfecting of the Saints, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> gifts God gave unto them, for the worke was not an imperfect thing, which Ministry ministred against the imperfect, &amp; to the perfecting, untill they mett all in the unity; So you that cry up imperfection, and yet are Ministers, what doe you minister that which is not perfect? then you cannot perfect the Saints. Do not you then declare your selves to all that be in the light to be Ministers of Sathan? And the world that hates the light which be in the darknes you cannot see for darknes is darknes, and the Ministers of Sathan are in the darknes, &amp; Ministers of darknes, who minister imperfect things. But the light is risen that manifests you all, and is the condemnation of all you that hate it, your works, your fruits, &amp; your Ministry &amp; the Ministers who the light it hate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am the light of the world, him by whom the world was made, and doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, if you love the light which you are enlightened withall, you love Christ, who saith,</hi> learne of me <hi>but if you hate that light, there is your Condemnation. From him who is one with the truth in every man, who of the Lord was moved this to write, that people might see what hath gotten up since the Apostles time out of the light with the light, and reigned out of the light, but now is manifest with the light, which the Apostles were in, is it seene, and to the Children of light now is manifest; whose name of the world is called</hi> G. F.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:168387:16"/>
            <p>IF the blood which you professe to be the blood of Christ, if it doth not cleanse you from all sinne, what differ you from the Papists, whose blood cleanseth not from all sinne, but must have a Purgatory at last; Are not you them here that make the blood of Christ <hi>of none effect?</hi> And your Ministry which is not <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints,</hi> what differs it from the Papists? And your Church which is full of spots &amp; blem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, what differs it from the Papists? And your faith which doth not give you victory over the world, what differeth it you from the Papists? is it not a dead faith, which doth not give victory over the world, yea or nay? And is not that a living faith that gives victory over the world to God, from whence it comes which is his gift which is perfect? And what doth your hope differ you from the Papists, which doth not purisie you, even as he is pure? And what doth your b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efe differ you from the Papists, which <hi>are not perfected for ever by the one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffering?</hi> And the Scripture saith, <hi>that they are perfected for ever who are sanctified by the one offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> And are they sanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied that are not perfected? And doth any owne the <hi>Offering,</hi> but such as owne sanctification and perfection?</p>
            <p>Whether by the Act 1<seg rend="sup">e.</seg>
               <hi>Eliza.</hi> cap. 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg> last clause, that of the 1<seg rend="sup">o</seg> of <hi>Mary</hi> be not repealed, which saith; <hi>That all Lawes, Statutes, and Ordinances, wherein or whereby any other Services, Administration of Sacraments or Common prayer, is is limited, established, or set forth to be used</hi> &amp;c. <hi>shall be henceforth void and of none effect;</hi> And that of the first of <hi>Mary</hi> is for the establishing of the Masse and all Popish Services; And whether <hi>Nicholas Hide</hi> when cheife Justice of <hi>England</hi> gave not his judgement that it was wholy repealed?</p>
            <p>Whether that Law was not made by a Popish Queene and a Popish Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, for the defence of the Popish Priests and Jesuites, in the exercise of the Popish Idolatrous Doctrines and Services against the Witnesse of God in the Protestants, which then test fied against both, and some in flames of fire?</p>
            <p>That whole body of Popery being said to be removed, whether that Law be not also nul and void, seeing the effect ceaseth with the cause, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, when that which is defended is taken away?</p>
            <p>Whether he that hath the Law hath not the supremacie, and so whether he that hath the Popish Law, hath not the supremacie of the Pope?</p>
            <p>And when did any of the Priests take the Oath of <hi>Abjuration,</hi> who have <hi>Maryes</hi> Law to guard them, or when was it tendered them? By which Law many of the servants of God are cast into prison, and for breach of that Law there remaine, and the Oath of <hi>Abjuration</hi> is given to them whom they know cannot sweare.</p>
            <p>Whether that which seekes the defence of that Law against the Witnesse of God now, and that which so defends by pretence thereof, be not of the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me nature, roote, and principle with that which made that Law, and was defended thereby, and seekes the supremacie that guarded the Priests and Jesuites? And whether the witnesse o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God that testifies now, and suffers by colour of that Law, be not the same with that which testified in the dayes of <hi>Mary,</hi> and by it suffered?</p>
            <p>Whether the priviledges of a Law exterd to any but those whom that Law qualifies thereunto, and makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pable thereof, and so whether the Prie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s now claiming the priviledges of <hi>Maries</hi> Law made for the defence of the Jesuites and Priests in the exercise of the Popish and Idolations D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines and Services, and being defended thereby against the witnesse of God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168387:16"/>testifying against them, doe not manifestly declare themselves to be such, and no Ministers of Jesus Christ, and whether they are otherwise to be esteemed and accounted off, seeing they have the sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emacie that g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ards the Priests and Jesuites?</p>
            <p>Whether the holy men of God, Prophets and Apostles from the dayes of righteous <hi>Abel</hi> on record in the Scripture ever persecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed any (shew one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) or s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught for or had recourse to a carnall weapon or law of man to defend or inforce their testimony, or did otherwise endeavour to approve themselves in what of truth they declared then to that of God in every mans conscience? Or whether they were not in all ages p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>secuted by those who sought for, and had recourse to, and stirred up and made use of the Law of man and carnall weapons against the testimony of the Lord in his Prophets and Apostles?</p>
            <p>If Q <hi>Maries</hi> law be repealed, is it your reasonablenesse it to have, it to uphold your Minist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y?</p>
            <p>If there cannot be a Ministry held up without Queene <hi>Maries</hi> Law, what was that ministry that suffered by her law, that was not by it guarded, but testified against it? And whether that which caused this Ministry to suffer by Q <hi>Maries</hi> law is not that which is in the unreasonablenes, out of the saith of our Lord Jesus Christ, which respects no mans person, which purifies the heart, and gives victory over the world? And whether there was not a Ministry that did suffer by her law when it was given forth? And whether those that take the oath of Abjuration to renounce Popery, must not renounce the Law that caused the Protestants to suffer, which is the Popes Supremacie? And whether it be the higher power unto which the soule must be subject yea or nay? And whether the Ministers of Christ have not their power from Christ, who saith, <hi>I will be with you to the end of the world?</hi> And whether it is not Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Law that causeth the Saints now to suffer, as it did in the dayes of Q. <hi>Mary?</hi> And whether Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Law is not the Priests defence to guard them, as it was Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Priests, and did them? And whether any of the Priests that are guarded with that law can take the Oath of Abjuration, which is against Popery and the Supremacy of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> but they must be sound false swearers against that which guards them? And let us see how the Priests of the world can get this Cloake off their backes?</p>
            <p>And whether that the reasonablenesse did not in all ages stand out of that, that did persecute, which had its instruction from God, both Law and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, not of man nor by man? And whether there was not a Ministry in all ages out of the life which got the forme in the unreasonablenes, which was stood against with the Spirit of God in them in whom it was, from which Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the words were declared, and they which were in the unreasonablenes got the forme but with the Spirit were judged.</p>
            <p>Was not Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Law made to limit the Spirit of God, though she called a Defender of the Faith, and was not her Law to guard that which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Spirit of God, and to hold it up which the Spirit of God witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed against? And is not the Spirit of God now to witnesse against that roote and branch, which was made against it to limit it? and all that which doth authorize that which limitts the Spirit of God and is against it? Against all that the Spirit of God stands a witnesse, its beginning, its ending, and its foundation, which is to be raced out? They who are here have the power
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168387:17"/>from God, who are in the Spirit of God, which to the Spirits in prison mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and are manifest and written in one anothers hearts by the Spirit of the living God, which Spirit is the Judge of all Popery and Popish wayes, lapps them up together and fathomes and comprehends and judgeth them and condemnes them and tramples upon them. So take away the Popish Law take away the Priests life. Now all may see what is in the Priests heart, for there is his guard by which the Saints are cast into prison, which cast them into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in the dayes of Q. <hi>Mary;</hi> For see how many Priests will preach without the Popish Law, and have a Spirit to defend their Ministry: Trie them here with the Oath of Abinration who cry against Popery, yet dare not venture their Ministry without Q <hi>Maries</hi> Law which guarded the Popery, and cry against Jesuites, yet dare not venture their Ministry but as they are guarded by that Law that guarded the Jesuites?</p>
            <p>And what doe you Priests thinke of those Protestants that suffered by Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Law, which now is your Guard by which many of the Saints were and are by you cast into prison, and can you cry against Popery, and yet cry to her Law to protect you without hypocrisie? And if you say you renounce Popery, then rencunce Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Law. When shall we see a Priest deny Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Law, the authority of Q <hi>Maries</hi> Church, and then among the Papists to Minister, to draw them from under Popery up to Christ, whose blood cleanseth from all sinne, and so shall not looke for a Purgatorie, he that doth this must be one that riseth from the dead, who hath his power from God, and comes to life, who breakes downe all the dead Images and Crosses and likenesses; who is here, witnesseth Christ with him to the end of the world, marke, to the worlds end, that is farre beyond Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Act or Authority or Supremacie, or all the Popes power and authority, but who is in this power of the Lord Jesus defaceth it all and sees before the world was and it was, and he is with them who is the wisdome of God and the power of God, by which they answer that of God in every man, the light which brings them out of all visible things to Christ from whence the light comes, him by whom the world was made before it was made, for to be carnally minded is death, &amp; that goes from the light which comes from Christ, and so the mind being in the death it imitates Crosses and setts up an image and likenes, and bowes downe to that, a likenes set up he who is from the light, but he who is guided by the light with the light which comes from Christ up to Christ, here is the crosse to keepe the mind out of all things that are carnall or bending to them, with the light up to Christ, who is eternal which changeth not, and here the mind is spirituall, where there is peace out of all the worlds power and authority in the power and authority of Christ. That which is out of the light is out of the power and out of the truth, out of the light in the carnall, in the enmity where the murtherer is, out of the light where the likenes of truth which is not truth, that which is out of the light: So that which is out of the light is out of the truth, having a likenesse of truth not the truth, but is the death and enmity, that power is of selfe and of the Devill, and is with the light con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, which from Christ doth come, to whom all power in heaven and earth is given, which power judgeth the other, which is out of the light out of the truth and abides not in it.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>